guess who's back with another barbell
comparison spoiler alert it's me no two
barbells are identical so it can be a
little difficult when going to decide
which one you want for your home gym so
today i've got two awesome barbells that
i think you should definitely consider
adding to your home gym i've got the
ever popular and the fan favorite rogue
ohio bar and a lesser known but
impressively built and priced
x training elite competition barbell i
can't wait to put both of these barbells
head to head for you guys let's get
right to it
[Music]
what's up everybody it's jake back in
the barbing garage gym and for today's
video i've got the rogue ohio bar and
the x training elite competition barbell
in this review i'm gonna compare these
two and i'm gonna help you decide which
one needs to be in your home gym but
before i get going we've reviewed a lot
of barbells on barbin.com and if you
want to browse our best list just go
ahead and search barbind best barbells
and our list is going to pull right up
for you and you can find out which ones
we like the best
[Music]
so let's kick this video off with the
similarities between these two barbells
it's worth mentioning right up front
with you all that these are both
multi-purpose bars so they do in fact
have a lot of the same qualities now
let's talk about the knurling first
both knurlings here on these bars on the
moderate side of things it's going to be
really nice for those high rep movements
or anything like you know power clean
for instance anything where the bars are
going to rotate in your hands neither
one of these are gonna tear you up which
is pretty nice it's also really nice for
beginners as well you don't have those
calluses built up you know it's gonna be
just a nice touch for you now
you have bronze bushings in both of the
loading sleeves it's gonna give them a
nice spin for those power cleans any of
those olympic crossfit style lifts kind
of adding to the versatility here of
these bars but they don't spin out of
control so that's super nice because you
know it's also going to make these
versatile bars because you can
absolutely use these for power lift
movements you don't have to worry about
the sleeves just starting to spin so
don't worry about that here that's super
nice there's not a center knurling on
either one of these barbells
really common with multi-purpose bars
such as these you know because you're
often doing some olympic crossfit style
lifts and you know without that there
you really you know don't run the risk
of irritating your skin over time any of
those lifts that the bar tends to rub
against you now i will say
that could be a problem for some people
as you go to do a back squat because you
know you don't have that center knurling
it's going to give you more grip and
keep that bar in place and some people
actually enjoy having that center
knurling there while they're doing their
power cleans because once again that bar
is going to stick to you a little bit
more
last thing here the similarities both of
these bars do have dual neural markings
that's super nice it's just going to
allow you to get you know identical hand
placement as you go to get set up for
your wide lifts
[Music]
okay so what about the differences
between these two barbells well for
starters let's talk about the knurling
yeah i know i just said they're both on
the moderate side of things but they're
still pretty different now with rogue
they did use a volcano style knurling so
each individual marking is going to give
you four points of contact on your hand
that's going to be really the the best
in my opinion because you just have a
bigger surface area on your hand now
this x training bar it's
pretty smooth you know you can
definitely tell the knurling is there
it's just not cut very deep and that's
not to say this ohio bar is cut deep
it's not i don't think it is it's not
going to tear up your hands but compared
to the two this definitely is cut a
little bit deeper in my opinion
and i think also the black chrome that's
on this barbell is factoring in with
that grip as well i think it's kind of
interfering a little bit while you know
this is stainless steel and there's no
coating you don't have to worry about
that okay so
both of the sleeves are pretty similar
you know they both do have bronze
bushings they both have a grooved
pattern on the sleeve that's going to
help in terms of keeping your plates
locked into their original placement but
you know running my hands over both of
them
the higher bar it's it's cut deeper in
my opinion and you know once you really
get your hands on it you can tell now
tinsel strength is also a pretty
noticeable difference between these two
bars now with the ohio bar it's worth
mentioning there's multiple options for
you to choose from
those options are going to have a
tensile strength rating of 190 000 psi
while this stainless steel
version of the ohio bar has a 200 000
psi tensile strength rating now with
this x training elite competition bar it
has a rating of 215 000 psi so that's a
pretty big gap
[Music]
okay so now let's talk about your coding
options as well as price and just kind
of how that's going to factor in with
everything so it's worth mentioning that
with the x training elite competition
bar this is a black chrome finish it's
all you have to work with with this
barbell now with the ohio bar you've got
a couple different options that you're
working with that's also going to play a
factor in the price for each individual
option so we have the stainless steel
version of the ohio bar it's what we're
using for this video all the comparisons
we're making we're basing it off of this
stainless steel bar now we have chrome
sleeves on ours so this one's about 370
bucks if you wanted the stainless steel
sleeves to give you a fully stainless
steel build from sleeve to sleeve that's
going to be another 100 bucks or so once
you tack on shipping you're looking at
spending around 500 on this barbell
while with this black chrome finish on
the x training elite competition bar
it's like 230 bucks and shipping is free
so
literally about half the price
of the ohio bar so pretty big price gap
between these two barbells if you're
interested in the other versions of the
ohio bar there's a black zinc and a
e-coat that's going to cost you around
there's a black oxide version that's
around 320 and there's a custom bar it's
around 350 and you can customize nearly
anything you want about that bar
if you're sold on the ohio bar though i
would definitely just recommend going
with the stainless steel because it's
going to fight off rust and corrosion
really at the highest rate possible
and that's something that you know is
important in my opinion especially if
you're in a humid garage like i am where
all my equipment is stored that's going
to be a really big factor sticking with
that now
black chrome right here on this bar it's
going to help a little bit you know it's
better than you know some bare steel on
a barbell but you know in terms of
optimal resistance it just isn't going
to get it done for me personally because
i am in a pretty humid garage gym here
in nashville but you know if you were to
have all your equipment stored in a nice
climate controlled environment doesn't
get too hot and humid this could be just
fine for you you might not have to clean
it as much as i will which
gonna have to be a couple times a month
just to keep it in good shape which is
something that i really don't have to
worry about very much with this
stainless steel ohio bar
no that's something that's really a big
factor to me and i really think that's
what's driving that major price
difference between these two barbells
and i'll talk more about price here in a
second but
you know the tensile strength here with
the x training bar like i said it's 15
000 psi higher than this stainless steel
ohio bar so
you would think it'd be the other way
around but i really like i said i think
it's the stainless steel that's driving
that price difference
okay so let's talk a little bit more
about the price now with these two
barbells now once again this stainless
steel bar we don't have
the stainless steel sleeves but if you
did you know that's gonna be around 500
either way you're spending close to 500
on this barbell while with the x
training elite competition bar it's 230
bucks and shipping is free
now i know you know nearly 500 on a
barbell is a lot of money
believe it or not there's a couple
barbells out there that are more
expensive than the ohio bar but when it
comes to the x training elite
competition bar
i think you're going to be really hard
pressed to find a deal as good as this
one considering the tensile strength
rating i just personally have not seen
that so you know that's a really good
selling point here now if you don't want
to spend you know the money up front on
either one of these barbells you can
definitely finance your purchase and you
know make monthly payments and pay it
off over time so with the ohio bar
rogue's going to allow you to use pay
later from paypal as well as a firm
you know really doesn't matter which
option you go with you're going to be
looking at spending around 130 bucks a
month and with x training bar you can
use a firm and that's going to be around
60 a month now with a firm it's worth
mentioning that they do run a soft
credit score check on you it's not going
to affect your score but you know
depending on your score you might
actually have payments a little bit
higher than what i just mentioned that's
just something worth telling you guys
now if price is your main deciding
factor between these two barbells you
got to give the x training bar the nod
here because it's literally half the
price of the ohio bar and that tensile
strength is also higher than the ohio
bar
now at the same time you know this is a
stainless steel build of this bar and in
terms of fighting off rust and corrosion
this is what you want this is the
optimal choice you're not gonna have to
clean it as much as you will with the x
training bar and
that's something that a lot of you might
not want to do it doesn't take very long
but it still can be a bit of a process
for some people
and you know with this stainless steel
build you're not gonna have to do that
as much and it could actually wind up
lasting you longer than this one will
okay so let's talk about the build now
and some of the features that you're
gonna find with both of these barbells
but i'm gonna start with the ohio bar
once again it's a stainless steel really
high quality build and it does have
bronze bushings in the sleeves it's
gonna allow them to spin at a controlled
rate it's gonna be nice for those
olympic style lifts but as you can see i
mean it doesn't spin out of control so
you can still power lift that's really
really nice and it's important that they
do spin as you get to do those power
cleans because it's going to decrease
the amount of torque that your wrists
and your elbows have to go through
during those movements
now the knurling it's a volcano pattern
as i mentioned i personally think this
is the best pattern you could have on a
barbell because each individual marking
has four points of contact on your hands
and you know it's just a bigger surface
area so i think it's going to give you a
better grip
it's not too abrasive but you know i did
say comparing to the x training bar
it is cut more deep now it's not going
to tear you up
at all hasn't torn me up but you know
like i said it is a little bit more
abrasive than this other one it is rated
to hold up to 1 260 pounds which is a
nice number and once again that tensile
strength rating is 200 000 psi while
with the other coating options of this
bar they're 190 000 psi it's 86 inches
in length you have 16.4 inch loading
sleeves and then the handle diameter
here is 28 and a half millimeters
all right so let's transition to the x
training bar now it's the alloy steel
build and it has a tensile strength
rating of 215 000 psi that's really
solid sparse coated in black chrome
which i really like the look but in
terms of fighting off rust and corrosion
in a hot garage like i'm in this really
isn't going to be the optimal choice for
me
not like this stainless steel build with
the ohio bar
you also have bronze bushings in the
sleeves here gives you a nice controlled
spin they do spin a little bit more
freely than the ohio bar but it's not
too out of control it's still going to
be able to handle your power lifting
movements
you technically do have grooves right
here you can feel them they're
definitely there
they're not cut very deep and you know i
always say this i just said it a second
ago you definitely want some weight
collars no matter how your sleeves are
but that's especially true with this one
the knurling
is pretty passive in my opinion i know i
said it's on the moderate side and yeah
that's true but
it's just not very grippy for me it
could be different for you but my hands
tend to sweat a lot it gets hot in here
and
you know this isn't going to provide
that optimal grip for me it's just not
very abrasive so any of you power
lifters you know you can do all those
movements but this probably isn't going
to provide that optimal grip that you
want so i would suggest getting some
lifting chalk or maybe some straps or
potentially even some gloves just to
help you out a little bit this bar is
the 20 kilogram version there also is a
15 kilogram version so for this 20
kilogram it's 86 inches in length 16.4
inch loading sleeves and it has a 28
millimeter diameter you know there's two
different options more people can find a
version of this bar while that's not the
case with the ohio bar you only have
that 20 kilogram version
[Music]
okay so which barbell should you go with
well when looking to make a decision
between these two barbells there's four
factors i think that you really need to
consider the money
the tensile strength the materials used
and the grip that you're gonna get from
the knurling all right so let's talk
about the money first
no secret there's a pretty big price gap
between these two barbells you know the
rogue ohio bar the stainless steel build
specifically
it's gonna be nearly double the amount
of money that you're going to spend on
the x training bar so
you know if money is your big factor
here i'd probably just consider
saving that money and going with the x
training bar
you know when you look at the tensile
strength ratings you would think this
one would be more expensive but that's
clearly not the case now let's stick
with the tensile strength you know the x
training bar
higher has a higher rating than the
rogue ohio bar
215 000 as opposed to the 200 000 with
the stainless steel and 190 000 from the
other option now the materials used
really important to me personally
you know i'm in a pretty hot humid
garage
and those black chrome's really just not
going to get it done for me personally
because i'm going to have to clean it
more often than i will with this
stainless steel so if you're like me
might not want to take that risk and you
might just want to go ahead and you know
find something like this stainless steel
that's just gonna you know give you that
protection and possibly even last longer
than this black chrome will last you
lastly
the grip from the knurling
yeah they're both a little bit on the
moderate side of things but i think it's
pretty hard to ignore that the ohio bar
is
more abrasive than the x training
competition bar
it just feels better in my hands you
know my hands tend to sweat while i'm
working out and i don't really feel
compromised with my grip ever with this
bar but with this x training barbell
i have to wipe my hands off a good
amount just to continue getting that
good grip so that's something you really
got to think about as well all things
considered if i had to choose
i'm gonna have to go through the ohio
bar yeah it's more expensive but i'd
rather spend that extra money to get a
barbell that's gonna give me that
optimal resistance from rust and
corrosion in this humid garage it's
gonna give me that sticky tack grip that
i'm looking for and it still has a high
enough tensile strength rating to handle
everything that i'm throwing at it
all right well that's a wrap on today's
comparison over the rogue ohio bar and
the x training elite competition barbell
y'all these are two really solid options
for you to consider to add to your home
gym when you're looking for that new
barbell you know they both have moderate
knurling and they both utilize bronze
bushings both of those qualities are
going to make these really versatile
barbells and you know while the x
training bar does have a higher tensile
strength rating and it's about half the
price of the ohio
i still got to go with the ohio bar you
know i am in a pretty humid garage and i
need that extra protection from
corrosion and plus the grip here is
better for me personally as my hands
begin to sweat i don't feel compromised
so this is just worth that extra money
in my opinion
now you know at the same time
the tensile strength rating of the x
training competition bar you know it's
rated 215 000 psi which is really really
solid so
you know if that's a huge factor for you
you also want to save some money
you don't have sweaty hands like i do
and you know your equipment is in a more
controlled climate than this garage is
this could be a really solid option for
you i just personally like i said need
that extra protection from corrosion i
don't want to have to worry about that
forming on my bar like i will with this
black chrome
thanks for watching everybody i hope
this video was really helpful and that i
was able to give you some more insight
on both of these barbells and maybe even
help you decide which one you want to
add to your home gym
as always stay posted for my next review
but for now head over to barbin.com and
you can read more about this comparison
just search barbind rogue ohio bar
versus x training elite competition
barbell review
and you can read over everything we
discussed here today i'll see y'all next
time
you